A Guide to the Essex County (Va.) Deeds, Orders and Will Books, 1695-1793
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Essex County (Va.) Deed, Order and Will Books, 1695-1793
The Library of Virginia
Barcode numbers 1146436-1146449/Essex County (Va.) Reels 2-7 and 15-18 (Rappahannock County old)
14 v. (5631 p.)
Essex County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in a shipment of court papers from Essex County.
Historical Information
Essex County was formed in 1692 from Rappahannock County (old).
Scope and Content
Deed Books, 1695-1793 of Essex County Court. The deed book records the name of the grantor and grantee, the residence of both individuals and the description of property being sold or transferred. The volumes have indexes except (1707-1721) which contains the first and last names of both parties. It is arranged alphabetically from A-Z.
Order Books, 1699-1702, of Essex County Court. The order book records all matters brought before the court when it was in session. It provides a synopsis of cases in a neater, more organized form. These volumes are sometimes internally indexed; more rarely, there is a comprehensive index. A wide variety of information is found in this order book including: deeds, chancery causes, judgments, records of legal disputes heard before the county court and road orders. The volume has an index.
Will Books, 1699-1704 and 1716-1718, of Essex County Court. The will book includes the name of testator, list of heirs and year the wills were proven in court and probate records such as inventories and appraisements. All the will books have indexes except (1716-1718).
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Essex Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Essex County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Geographical Names:
Essex County (Va.) -- History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Deeds -- Virginia -- Essex County.; Judicial records-- Virginia -- Essex County.; Land records -- Virginia -- Essex County.; Local government records -- Virginia -- Essex County.; Order books -- Virginia -- Essex County.; Will books -- Virginia -- Essex County.; Wills -- Virginia -- Essex County.
Contents List
- Deeds, Etc. No. 9, 1695-1699 (Barcode 1146436)
- Deeds and Wills No. 10, Orders, 1699-1702 (Barcode 1146446)
- Deeds and Wills No. 11, 1702-1704 (Barcode 1146447)
- Deeds, Etc No. 13, 1707-1711 (Barcode 1146437)
- Deeds and Wills No. 15, 1711-1716 (Barcode 1146449)
- Deeds and Wills No. 14, 1711-1716 (Barcode 1146448)
- Deeds, Etc.No. 16, 1718-1721 (Barcode 1146438)
- Deeds, Etc. No. 19, 1728-1733 (Barcode 1146439)
- Deeds, Etc. No. 21, 1735-1738 (Barcode 1146440)
- Deeds, Etc. No. 23, 1742-1745 (Barcode 1146441)
- Deeds, Etc. No. 25, 1749-1752 (Barcode 1146442)
- Deeds and C No. 26, 1752-1754 (Barcode 1146443)